[
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 1,
        "year": 1989,
        "question": "<p>The major raw material in a plastic industry is</p>",
        "explanation": "<p>- Earlier, molasses act as a raw material which yield ethanol from which ETHENE (gotten is used to) produce a range of poly(ethene) plastics.</p><p>- Nowadays, starting new raw materials are obtained by the fractional distillation of crude oil or petroleum.</p><p>- During the thermal cracking of petroleum; long chain alkanes are converted into smaller chain alkanes, ALKENES (with Ethene being the predominate), etc.</p><p>- The Alkenes such as Ethene and Propene can be made into Poly(ethene) / plastic, nylon, etc.</p>",
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "ethanol",
            "sulphur",
            "methylethanoate",
            "ethene",
            "ethane"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 2,
        "year": 1989,
        "question": "Which of the following reactions represents the laboratory preparation of hydrogen?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "C<sub>(s)</sub>+ H<sub> 2 </sub>O<sub>(l)</sub>→ CO<sub>(g)</sub>+ H<sub>2(g)</sub>",
            "2Na<sub>(s)</sub>+ 2H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>(l)</sub>→ 2NaOH<sub>(aq)</sub>+ H<sub>2(g)</sub>",
            "Zn<sub>(s) + 2HCI<sub>(aq)</sub> → ZnCI<sub>2(aq)</sub> + H<sub>2(g)</sub>\n</sub>",
            "Cu<sub>(s)</sub>+ H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>(l)</sub>→ CuO<sub>(s)</sub>+ H<sub>2(g)</sub>",
            "2AI<sub>(s)</sub>+ 3H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>(l) → Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3(s)</sub> + 3H<sub>2(g)</sub>\n</sub>"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 3,
        "year": 1989,
        "question": "Which of the following statements best explains cracking ? It is a process",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "in which an alkene adds on itself repeatedly to form long chain polymers",
            "in which large hydrocarbon molecules are broken into smaller units",
            "for measuring theoctane number of petrol",
            "in which carbon chain results in a zigzag arrangement",
            "in which aromatic hydrocarbons are produced"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 4,
        "year": 1989,
        "question": "120cm<sup>3</sup>of hydrogen were sparked with 60cm<sup>3</sup>of oxygen at 110<sup>o</sup>C. What was the volume of stream produced? The equation for the reaction is 2H<sub>2(g)</sub>+ O<sub>2(g)</sub>→ 2H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>(g)</sub>",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "30cm<sub>3</sub>",
            "60cm<sub>3</sub>",
            "90cm<sub>3</sub>",
            "120cm<sub>3</sub>",
            "180cm<sub>3</sub>"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 5,
        "year": 1989,
        "question": "The earthly impurities in iron ore are removed in the blast furnace by the reaction",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "CO<sub>2</sub>+ C →2CO",
            "Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>+ 3CO →2Fe + 3CO<sub>2</sub>",
            "SiO<sub>2</sub>+ CaO →CaSiO<sub>3</sub>",
            "CaCO<sub>3</sub>→ CaO + CO<sub>2</sub>",
            "C +CO<sub>2</sub>→ CO<sub>2</sub>"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 6,
        "year": 1989,
        "question": "Which of the following hydrocarbons is not likely to be present in petrol?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "C<sub>14</sub>H<sub>30</sub>",
            "C<sub>10</sub>H<sub>22</sub>",
            "C<sub>9</sub>H<sub>20</sub>",
            "C<sub>7</sub>H<sub>16</sub>",
            "C<sub>5</sub>H<sub>12</sub>"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 7,
        "year": 1989,
        "question": "The most suitable method to use when separating an insoluble solid from a liquid is",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "evaporation",
            "filtration",
            "magnetization",
            "sublimation",
            "distillation"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 8,
        "year": 1989,
        "question": "<p>The following are miscible with water except</p>",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "ethylethanoate",
            "methanol",
            "ethanoic acid",
            "methanoic acid",
            "ethanol"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 9,
        "year": 1989,
        "question": "If 200cm<sup>3</sup>of a gas at s.t.p. has a mass of 0.268g, what is its molar mass? (Molar volume of a gas at s.t.p. = 22.4 dm<sup>3</sup>)",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "300g",
            "200g",
            "150g",
            "30g",
            "15g"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 10,
        "year": 1989,
        "question": "How many carbon atoms are there in a benzene ring?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "4",
            "5",
            "6",
            "7",
            "8"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 11,
        "year": 1989,
        "question": "Which of the following gases will bleach moist litmus paper?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "CI<sup>2</sup>",
            "CO<sup>2</sup>",
            "SO<sup>2</sup>",
            "HCI<sup>2</sup>",
            "N<sup>2</sup>O"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 12,
        "year": 1989,
        "question": "<p>Given that for the reaction KOH (aq) + HCI(aq) → KCI(aq) + H2O(L) H = - 54 Kj mol-1. What is the quantity of heat involved in the reaction?2NaOH(aq) + H2SO 4(aq) → Na2SO4(aq) + 2H 2O(l)?</p>",
        "explanation": "<p>Given that \\(KOH_{(aq)} + HCl_{(aq)} \\to KCl_{(aq)} + H_{2}O_{(l)} ; \\Delta H = -54 kJ/mol\\)</p><p>The standard heat of neutralization is the amount of heat evolved when 1 mole of hydrogen ion from an acid reacts with 1 mole of hydroxide ion from the base to form one mole of water, under standard conditions.</p><p>\\(\\therefore 2NaOH_{(aq)} + H_{2}SO_{4(aq)} \\to Na_{2}SO_{4(aq)} + 2H_{2}O_{(l)} ; \\Delta H = -(2 \\times 54 kjmol^{-1})\\)</p><p>\\(\\therefore \\Delta H = -108 kJmol^{-1}\\) </p>",
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "- 108Kj",
            "-54 kj",
            "-27 kj",
            "+27 kj",
            "+54 kj"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 13,
        "year": 1989,
        "question": "When an element can exist in two or more forms in the same physical state, the element is said to exhibit",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "isotopy",
            "isomerism",
            "allotropy",
            "hygroscopy",
            "sublimation"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 14,
        "year": 1989,
        "question": "Which of the following carbohydrates does NOT usually occur in the crystalline form?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 4,
        "options": [
            "Fructose",
            "Glucose",
            "Sucrose",
            "Maltose",
            "Cellulose"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 15,
        "year": 1989,
        "question": "Copper can best be purified by",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "roasting the impure copper in a blast furnace",
            "heating the oxide with coke",
            "electrolyzing a copper (ll) salt solution using the impure copper as the anode",
            "converting the impure copper to a trioxonitrate (V)",
            "washing the impure copper with sodium hydroxide solution"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 16,
        "year": 1989,
        "question": "Locally produced soap in which wood ash is used as the base is usually soft because the wood ash contains a lot of",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "sodium ions",
            "potassium ions",
            "lithium ions",
            "calcium ions",
            "magnesium ions"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 17,
        "year": 1989,
        "question": "Why is potassium fluoride added to the electrolyte in the extraction of sodium from fused sodium chloride?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "Pure sodium chloride does not conduct electricity",
            "Potassium fluoride prevents the sodium produced from attacking the electrodes",
            "Potassium fluride increases conductivity",
            "Potassium fluride reduces the temperature at which sodium chloride fuses",
            "the potassium fluride acts as a catalyst"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 18,
        "year": 1989,
        "question": "The rate of the hydrogen in the reaction Zn<sub>(s)</sub>+ 2HCI<sub>(aq)</sub>→ ZnCI<sub>2(g)</sub>+ H<sub>2(aq)</sub>+ H<sub>2(g)</sub>can be increased by",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "using Zinc powder instead of Zinc granules",
            "using dilute instead of concentrated hydrochloric acid",
            "cooling the container in which the mixture is placed",
            "using an alloy of zinc instead of pure zinc",
            "using hydrogen chloride gas instead of hydrochloric acid solution"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 19,
        "year": 1989,
        "question": "Octane number is highest in petrol containing a high proportion of",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 4,
        "options": [
            "heptane",
            "octane",
            "2-methylpentane",
            "2, 4-dimethylpentane",
            "2,2,4-trimethylpentane"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 20,
        "year": 1989,
        "question": "Given the following half-cell reaction; 2Cl<sub>(aq)</sub>→ CI<sub>2(g)</sub>+ 2e, how many mole of electrons will be required to produce 1.12dm<sup>3</sup>of chlorine gas at s.t.p? (Molar volume of a gas at s.t.p. = 22.4dm<sup>3</sup>)",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "1.00",
            "0.40",
            "0.20",
            "0.10",
            "0.01"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 21,
        "year": 1989,
        "question": "Which of the following is used extensively in manufacturing photographic chemicals?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "Aluminium chloride",
            "Zinc chloride",
            "Silver chloride",
            "Mercury (ll) chloride",
            "lron (ll) chloride"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 22,
        "year": 1989,
        "question": "Given that 1 mole of carbon -12 weighs 12.0g, how many atoms are there in 24.0g magnesium? (C = 12, Mg = 24, NA = 6.02 x 10<sup>23</sup>mol<sup>-1</sup>)",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "1/2 x 6.02 x 10<sup>23</sup>",
            "1 x 6.02 x10<sup>23</sup>",
            "2 x 6.02 x 10<sup>23</sup>",
            "3x 6.02 x 10<sup>23</sup>",
            "4x 6.02 x 10<sup>23</sup>"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 23,
        "year": 1989,
        "question": "What is the concentration, in mol dm<sup>3</sup>, of solution is allowed to evaporate the allotrope of sulphur formed is",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "plastic sulphur",
            "amorphous sulphur",
            "rhombic sulphur",
            "monoclinc sulphur",
            "colloidal sulphur"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 24,
        "year": 1989,
        "question": "If sulphur is dissolved in carbon (IV) sulphide and the solution is allowed to evaporate, the allotrope of sulphur formed is",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "plastic sulphur",
            "amorphous sulphur",
            "rhombic sulphur",
            "monoclinc sulphur",
            "colloidal sulphur"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 25,
        "year": 1989,
        "question": "<p>Given that for the reaction. N2(g) + 3H2(g) ⇌ 2NH3(g) ∆H = -92kJ. What is the enthalpy of formation of ammonia from its elements?</p>",
        "explanation": "<p>In the reaction the enthalpy of formation 2 mole of NH3 is - 92kJ. Therefore the standard \\(\\Delta H\\) of formation = \\(\\frac{-92kJ}{2} = -46KJmol^{-1}\\).</p>",
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "-46KJ mol<sup>-1</sup>",
            "-184KJmol<sup>-1</sup>",
            "-92KJmol<sup>-1</sup>",
            "184KJmol<sup>-1</sup>",
            "+46KJmol<sup>-1</sup>"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 26,
        "year": 1989,
        "question": "The following are s-block elements except",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 4,
        "options": [
            "lithium",
            "magnesium",
            "potassium",
            "calcium",
            "aluminium"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 27,
        "year": 1989,
        "question": "Which of the following statements is not true of tin? it",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "is a p-block element",
            "is extracted from cassiterite SnO<sub>2</sub>",
            "is used for protecting iron containers from corrosion",
            "combines with copper to form the alloy brass",
            "shows two oxidation states, + 2 and + 4 in most of its compounds"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 28,
        "year": 1989,
        "question": "What quantity of copper will be deposited by the same quantity of electricity that deposited 9.0g of aluminum? (A = 27, Cu = 64)",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "64g",
            "32g",
            "7.1g",
            "6.4g",
            "3.2g"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 29,
        "year": 1989,
        "question": "The electronic configuration of two atoms X and Y are as follows: X - 1s<sup>2</sup>2s<sup>2</sup>2p<sup>6</sup>3s<sup>1</sup>, Y -1s<sup>2</sup>2s<sup>2</sup>2p<sup>6</sup>3s<sup>2</sup>3p<sup>6</sup>4s<sup>2</sup>which of the statements below is true of the position of X and Y in the Periodic Table?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "x belongs to group 1, Y belongs to period 2,",
            "x belongs to group 1, Y belongs to period 4",
            "x belongs to group 2, Y belongs to period 1",
            "x belongs to group 3, Y belongs to period 2",
            "x belongs to group 3, Y belongs to period 4"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 30,
        "year": 1989,
        "question": "Which of the following is a condition for a spontaneous reaction?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "∆H -T is zero",
            "∆H-T∆ S is positive",
            "∆H-T∆ S is negative",
            "∆S is zero",
            "∆S is positive"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 31,
        "year": 1989,
        "question": "<p>50cm 3 of a saturated solution of potassium trioxonitrate (V)at 40°C contains 5.05g of the salt. What is the solubility of potassium trioxonitrate (V) at 40°C? (KNO3 = 101)</p>",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "1.0 mol dm<sup>-3</sup>",
            "1.5 mol dm<sup>-3</sup>",
            "2.0 mol dm<sup>-3</sup>",
            "2.5mol dm<sup>-3</sup>",
            "5.0mol dm<sup>-3</sup>"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 32,
        "year": 1989,
        "question": "The oxidation number of chlorine is + 1 in",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 4,
        "options": [
            "KCIO<sub>3</sub>",
            "CI<sub>2</sub>O<sub>7</sub>",
            "ZnCI<sub>2</sub>",
            "HCI",
            "NaCIO"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 33,
        "year": 1989,
        "question": "What is the voltage of the cell represented at Zn<sub>(s)</sub>Zn<sup>2+</sup><sub>(aq)</sub>/Cu<sup>2+</sup><sub>(aq)</sub>/Cu<sub>(s)</sub>given that for Cu<sup>2+</sup><sub>(aq)</sub>/ Cu<sub>(s)</sub>E<sub>o</sub>= 0.337V and for Zn<sup>2+</sup><sub>(aq)</sub>/Zn<sub>(s)'</sub>E<sub>o</sub>= -0.763V?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 4,
        "options": [
            "+0.426V",
            "-0.426V",
            "-0.337V",
            "-1.10V",
            "+1.10V"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    }
]